Guide to the Nixon Library Controversy Reference Collection, 1981-2001
Duke University. University Archives
Nixon Library Controversy Reference collection 1981-2001
Duke University. University Archives
1.0 linear feet Extent: 1,000 Items
This collection was compiled from a variety of sources by the University Archives for use in reference and research. Contains materials pertaining to the controversy surrounding Duke University President Terry Sanford's proposal to locate the presidential library of Richard Nixon (Duke Law '37) at Duke University. Types of materials include clippings, student papers, correspondence, minutes, reports, audiotapes, and a manual. Major subjects include Duke University, the Academic Council, the Board of Trustees, Richard M. Nixon, Terry Sanford, presidential libraries, and libraries on campus. Materials range in date from 1981-2001.
uanixonlibref
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Provenance
The Nixon Library Controversy Reference Collection was compiled from various sources by University Archives staff for reference and research.
Historical Note
In July 1981, Terry Sanford initiated negotiations with former U. S. President Richard Nixon (Duke Law '37) to locate the Nixon presidential library on the campus of Duke University, Nixon's alma mater. When this information was revealed to faculty members during the week of August 10, 1981, many opposed the proposition, citing Sanford's failure to consult the faculty prior to initiating negotiations.
Many who opposed the library had moral objections to memorializing a President whose behavior in office was reproachable, and they feared a negative effect on the university's reputation. Other concerns included the effects of increased tourist traffic on campus and the uncertain aesthetic nature of the proposed structure. However, supporters of the Nixon Library argued that the scholarly and academic benefits of locating the Nixon Presidential Materials collection on campus should and would outweigh other concerns. These supporters tended to denounce the actions of vocal dissenters as divisive and arrogant.
Meetings of the Academic Council and Board of Trustees during September and October 1981 were dominated by the Nixon Library debate, and a group of faculty formed the Committee Against the Nixon-Duke Library (CANDL) to organize the efforts of faculty, students, alumni, and others opposed to the proposed library. Although the Academic Council voted not to pursue further negotiations with former president Nixon in a 35-34 decision at a September 3, 1981 meeting, the Board of Trustees later voted 9-2 to proceed. By April 1982, negotiations had stalled. One year later, Nixon's representatives announced that a site at Chapman College in San Clemente, California, had been chosen for the Richard M. Nixon Presidential Library.
Collection Overview
This collection contains clippings, student papers, correspondence, minutes, reports, audiotapes, and a manual concerning the proposed Nixon presidential library at Duke University. Contains personal correspondence of Terry Sanford and various Academic Council and Board of Trustees members, as well as correspondence to and from the Council and Board as a whole. Also included are minutes and tape recordings from Academic Council meetings, reports made to the Political Science Department and the Environmental Concerns Committee, and a chronology of events from July through September 1981. Clippings from local and national publications are arranged chronologically. Two student papers are included (1982 and 1985). General presidential library information includes a briefing book, handbook, and period publications from other presidential libraries. Also contains an inventory and processing manual for the Richard M. Nixon Presidential Materials, provided by the National Archives and Records Service. Materials range in date from 1981-2001.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Duke University. Academic Council; Duke University -- Alumni and alumnae.; Duke University. Board of Trustees.; Duke University. Committee Against the Nixon-Duke Library.; Duke University. Nixon Library Committee.; Duke University -- Faculty.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994; Presidential libraries -- United States.; Sanford, Terry, 1917- 1998
Related Material
Nixon Library Controversy collection 1981-2001
University Archives, Duke University.
Richard M. Nixon Reference Collection, 1934-1999
University Archives, Duke University.
Committee Against the Nixon-Duke Library (CANDL) Records, 1981
University Archives, Duke University.
Detailed Description of Collection
- Container List
  - Correspondence - Terry Sanford, 1981 Aug 12 - Oct 31 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Academic Council & Board of Trustees, 1981, Aug 17 - Dec 15
  - Academic Council Meetings - Audiotapes, 1981 Sep 3-11
  - Academic Council Minutes & Reports, 1981 Aug 31 - Oct 29
  - Miscellaneous Reports, 1981 Aug - Nov
  - Miscellaneous Minutes & Resolutions Chronology
  - Presidential Libraries - Handbook & General Information
  - Presidential Libraries - Briefing Book
  - Presidential Libraries - Publications/Brochures
  - Clippings, 1981 Aug (Box 2)
  - Clippings, 1981 Sep 1-4
  - Clippings, 1981 Sep 5-16
  - Clippings, 1981 Sep 17-30
  - Clippings, 1981 Oct
  - Clippings, 1981 Nov-Dec
  - Clippings, 1982 Jan-Aug
  - Clippings and Articles, 1983-2001
  - Student Papers, 1982 & 1985
    - Palmer, Bonnie E. Decision-Making at Duke University Regarding the Acceptance of Nixon's Papers. 1982.
    - Philipsen, Dirk. The Nixon Library Controversy at Duke: Power, Politics, and a Private Elite University. 1985.
  - Nixon Presidential Materials - Inventory & Processing Manual